The opening range breakout is one of the
most trading strategies out there. The
idea is super simple. I think it's easy
for people to understand, so it's really
popular. All you have to do is mark the
high and low of the first 15 minutes, 30
minutes, 60 minutes, whatever range
you're trading. You mark the the high
and low of the range of the session that
you're trading. You wait for price to
break above or below those levels. You
take a trade. Sounds easy, right? The
problem is that most traders lose money
with it. It's not because the strategy
doesn't work. I use it. I make a lot of
money with a strategy. The problem is
that most traders are treating it the
wrong way. So, today I'm going to talk
about the three biggest mistakes that I
see traders making with the opening
range breakout. I'm going to talk about
how to avoid them. And then I'm actually
going to show you some real-life
examples and a couple of tricks, some
things that I add to my chart so I get
extra confluence for when I want to take
the trade. All right, let's dive into
it.
So, real quick, here is our range. Let
me get our my drawing tool here. Let's
say this is the first couple minutes of
price action.
And then we draw our range. This is our
range high.
And this is our range low. All right?
So, for the sake of this example, I'm
going to be using the 15-minute opening
range. We'll talk about different range
options in one of the mistake number
three.
Um but this is our range. So, let's say
this is the first 15 minutes of the
session that I'm trading. I trade the
New York session. This works for London.
It works for any of the sessions that
you want to use. So, the first mistake,
the biggest mistake by far, is that when
price finally pushes outside of the
range, people get excited. So, if it
breaks out of the range high, people get
excited. They push the buy button, and
then within minutes, price is right back
inside of the range. You get stopped
out, and you wonder what happened.
Here's what happened. The market often
finds easy liquidity levels to stop
people out. So, retail traders, they
place buy stops right at the high, and
sell stops right at the low, and
institutions know this. So, many times
price will push through that level
just enough to trigger orders before
deciding whether it actually wants to
continue. So, I don't like chasing the
initial breakout. What I do is I let the
market show its hand. So, I wait and see
which end of the range breaks, if it
breaks out to the top or the bottom, and
then I want to see a pullback. So, in
this case, if buyers really are in
control,
it's definitely like if it does get a
pullback, it's going to find support at
some point. This, for one, gives me a
better entry.
I have a smaller stop loss, so I have a
better risk reward, and then the confirm
There's more confirmation that the move
is real. So, the trade isn't the
breakout. The trade The better trade is
often the retest.
Sure, you'll miss some runners. There's
going to be days where it just explodes
out and never retest. You're going to
miss some runners, for sure.
But you're also going to
avoid a lot of false breakouts. All
right? So, that's mistake number one.
Mistake Mistake number two is ignoring
the bigger market context. So, a
breakout, we're looking at, you know,
the 15-minute range in the greater
context of an hourly chart, 4-hour
chart. So, you have to ask, "What is the
market doing overall?
Are we trending higher?
Like right? Like Are we below major
levels? Maybe we have
like a key
Let me get my uh uh drawing tool here.
Maybe we have like a key resistance
level right here. And you're trying to
trade a breakout into this resistance,
right? Or maybe we have VWAP, if you're
a VWAP trader, which I am. Maybe VWAP is
like right below the opening range right
here.
And then if we're taking a short right
into VWAP, which is a lot of times going
to be a support. Right? You're taking a
short into a support. Or maybe what's
the slope of VWAP? Is VWAP super flat?
Right? What's the greater uh market
context? Are we inside of a larger
range? Like maybe the hour the last hour
or 4-hour chart, we're kind of in this
box, right? We're in a range. So the the
the possibility of a breakout is not
very likely. In that case, I actually
trade the false breakout a lot. So
you can either trade the opening range
break, like I said in example one, where
it breaks out, it retests a level, and
I'll show you a trick for that in a
second. Retests a level, you take a
trade on the continuation.
Or you can take what I call a fake
breakout. So in this case, like it broke
out, it hit this key high level higher
time frame resistance, you could
potentially take a short. So that's the
mark mistake number two is ignoring the
greater the higher time frame market
context. So I always have my VWAPs on my
chart, the daily VWAP, the New York
anchored VWAP, and the weekly VWAP, so I
can see what the greater market market
context is. I also put key levels on my
chart. So previous day high and low,
Asia high and low, London high and low,
so I can see if we're getting into a
resistance or a support area. I don't
want to be trading into that. All right?
So, then look at as we are flat, is it
trending?
Those are all usually warning signs,
okay? So, sometimes the best trade is no
trade at all. If any of those are giving
you conflicting information, then don't
take a breakout trade.
Mistake number three, and then I'll get
into some actual examples and some
tricks for how I trade this uh strategy
with you guys. Mistake number three is
using the wrong opening range.
A lot of traders use the 5-minute
opening range, which in my opinion is
too volatile. There's still too much
liquidity sweeps and the algos and all
that. It's It's not a good safe
strategy. So, 15 minutes is the minimum
opening range that I would uh
recommend that you trade. A lot of
people also do the 30-minute.
And then I also trade the 60-minute
opening range, which is also called the
initial balance. So, I actually have two
ranges that I trade, the 15-minute and
the 60-minute. And both of them I trade
very similarly, all right? So, these
levels become extremely important for
the rest of the session. The key is
consistency. Whatever time frame you
decide to mark off, the key is
consistency. That way you can get to
know your session, you can know your
ticker, you can become familiar with how
price reacts at those levels. The market
rewards repetition and preparation.
All right? So, final thoughts before I
get into some examples. Actually, let's
dive into some examples really quick
first. And then I'll kind of recap it
for you guys.
All right. So, I have my indicator on
here
um showing you guys
the 15-minute opening range for the New
York session, all right? The yellow line
is the high and the low for the opening
range.
Let's look at some examples here. So,
this is a good example of mistake number
one, just buying the breakout, right?
So, here, this candle right here
actually broke out of the 15-minute
opening range low. So, those retail
traders that I said, there's actually
some YouTubers out there that recommend
this as a strategy, and it's terrible. I
hope you guys aren't doing it, but
there's some people that will place a
buy stop order. So, as soon as it breaks
out of the bottom of the range, you're
in a short automatically. Same thing at
the top. They place a buy stop order at
the top, as soon as it breaks the high,
it's going to you're going to be in a
long.
In this example right here, look, it
barely wicked out, and then it retraced
all the way to the middle of the range
before continuing.
So, mistake number one, right? You
probably would have gotten super
emotional, probably would have moved
your stop loss a little bit, like, "Oh
my gosh, too much risk." Why not wait
for a retrace,
and then get a better entry, better risk
reward, right? More confirmation. So,
let me show you a trick for this. What I
do is I throw VWAP onto my chart. So, I
use a an
indicator from EdgeWon. This So, this is
a paid indicator, but you can do the
same thing manually. So, this dark blue
line right here, that's my daily VWAP,
so it's anchored at the set as 6:00 p.m.
open each day. And then this light blue
line is the New York anchored VWAP, so
it's anchored at the opening candle for
the session. You can do the same thing
with the London open as well.
But, what I do is I wait for the
breakout of the opening range, and then
I wait for the retest of either the New
York either VWAP or the midpoint of the
range. So, let me throw on my Fibonacci
here.
Just to see where the 50% of the range
is. And look, they're right in the same
zone. The anchored VWAP and the 50% is
right in the same range. So, when it
comes up to this zone, this is a much
better entry, a much better
risk-to-reward than if I had entered
here, right? So, I'll show you the
difference. If you entered here,
so there's our first scenario, you enter
right at the break of the range. You're
going to need to give yourself a wide
stop loss to give it room to potentially
retrace, right? So, you want to put it
above the
midpoint of the range cuz it could come
there, it could come a little higher, so
maybe that's where you put your stop
loss.
And then, if you're looking for like a
two-to-one,
you have to go all the way down to here.
Or, if you're going to be a little more
conservative and go for a one-to-one,
there you go. Let's say you go for a
one-to-one. That's your trade if you're
taking the initial break out of the
range.
Versus my strategy, where you wait for
the retest, you're going to get a better
entry because you wait for the retrace
to the New York anchored VWAP and or the
the midpoint of the range. So, I would
wait for it to bounce at the New York
anchored VWAP.
I can have a little bit of a tighter
stop loss, right? So, this is like a
78-point stop loss versus the other one
was a 149-point
stop loss.
And then, I can either target the bottom
of the range, which is a super safe,
like really high win rate strategy.
That's a one-to-one. Or, I can go for
more like a two-to-one. So, better
risk-to-reward, right? Now, I'm making
on the on NQ 155 points off of that
trade.
And it hit. And it could potentially go
lower. So, that's an example of mistake
number one. Why not wait for a retrace?
Yes, like I said, there's the the the
chance that you're going to miss the
breakout, but if you back test this,
you'll see that the number of times that
you avoid the loss are outnumbered by
the amount of wins and the higher win
rate, the higher risk reward that you
get for waiting for that retrace.
So, hopefully that makes sense and
hopefully that gives you a little bit of
a good insight into the trick that I use
on my entries. All right, so here's
another example.
Right here,
it breaks out of the 15-minute opening
range.
It comes back and it retests this
anchored view up.
You can get in here,
put your stop loss below that recent
wick,
target a two to one.
There you go, that was a win.
As far as the target, what I do, this is
everyone's different on their targets.
You can go to a two to one, three to
one. You could also look for
look left for a level that makes sense.
So, maybe there's like a London high or
an Asia high or previous day high or
some sort of consolidation zone or
supply zone or to the left that you want
to target, all right? So, that's how I
do it. I I do a target that makes sense.
All right, so I don't want to bore you
guys with too many examples. Hopefully
that makes sense, but my final thoughts
on this strategy is that the opening
range trading strategy is not broken.
Most traders are just simply executing
it poorly. So, the three biggest
mistakes to recap, chasing the breakout
instead of waiting for confirmation,
ignoring the higher time frame market
context, and then using random opening
ranges without understanding why and how
price moves and not being consistent
with it.
So, I'll tell you the market really it
loves to trap impatient traders. Um but
wait for confirmation, right? Patience
is your edge. Trade with the greater top
context in mind and then remember
there's always another setup tomorrow.
So, if there is one of those days where
it just goes and it never retests, oh
well, let it go. There's always another
opportunity, right? All right, you guys.
See you in the next one.